{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This younger sister of Sybilla was dismissed as a \"great Flanders mare.\" This woman lived in Richmond castle after a generous settlement. This daughter of John the Simple was wed in the Palace of Placentia, her husband's birthplace, in 1540. Because the marriage of this continental European was never consummated, she got a real annulment, unlike Catherine Howard two years later. For 10 points, name this fourth wife of England's Henry VIII, who was born in what's now Germany.",
      "answer": "Anne of Cleves <MJ> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's name appears in the subtitle of the James Carville book …and the Horse he Rode In On. This president of Baylor University represented the school board in the case of Morse v. Frederick, also known as the \"Bong Hits 4 Jesus\" case. He created a report on the death of deputy White House counsel Vince Foster and the Whitewater scandal. For 10 points, name this independent counsel who investigated Monica Lewinsky's affair with Bill Clinton.",
      "answer": "Kenneth Starr <MC> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Practitioners of this religion traditionally drape thrones with red, white, and blue. Priestly initiates of this religion must collect shell necklaces called elekes. Members of this religion were involved in the court case Church of the Lukumi Babalu Aye v. City of Hialeah, which dealt with the right to a certain practice undertaken in iles, or places of worship. For 10 points, name this syncretic Caribbean religion that venerates Orishas and has gained notoriety for its practice of animal sacrifice.",
      "answer": "Santeria <AK> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader displaced an indigenous group called the Montagnards from the Central Highlands in an attempt to hold back invaders. Cable 243, which authorized a coup against this leader, was sent to his ambassador Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr. This man authorized the use of liquid tear gas against protesters in Hue. This man's soldiers brutally targeted his country's Buddhist majority. For 10 points, name this controversial Catholic leader of South Vietnam.",
      "answer": "Ngo Dinh Diem <KG> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This waterway’s Brecksville Dam feeds a historic recreational canal. A national park on the banks of this river features the Towpath Trail and was declared in 1974. A 1969 event here caused by an oil slick near the Republic Steel Mill led TIME to describe it as a river where “one does not drown but decays.” Its most famous image was actually from a 1952 conflagration. For 10 points, what river, which empties into Lake Erie in downtown Cleveland, often caught fire?",
      "answer": "Cuyahoga River <CW> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "question": "The most important victory of Tettius Julianus was against these people at the Second Battle of Tapae. A war against these people spurred the formation of the Thirtieth, or Ulpia Victrix, Legion. While they were led from Sarmizegethusa by Decebalus, a bridge built by Apollodorus of Damascus helped Roman armies defeat these people by crossing the Danube en masse. For 10 points, name these rivals of the emperors Domitian and Trajan, a tribe of what's now Romania.",
      "answer": "Dacians <MJ> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "The New York Times claimed that a war against this tribe was \"a gigantic blunder and a crime.\" Yellow Wolf, a warrior of this tribe, dictated a memoir to Lucullus McWhorter. In this tribe's namesake war, it lost the Battle of Bear Paw, which occurred after warriors passed through Yellowstone National Park. In October 1877, a leader of this tribe declared \"I will fight no more forever.\" For 10 points, name this Pacific Northwest tribe led by Chief Joseph.",
      "answer": "Nez Perce <MC> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This object travels to Narragonia in a 1494 German satire by Sebastian Brant. The start of Michel Foucault's Madness and Civilization discusses the popularity of this artistic motif in the Renaissance. Death and the Miser was probably once part of a triptych with a painting of this object by Hieronymus Bosch, in which it has a thin tree for a mast. For 10 points, name this allegorical vehicle which sails the rivers and seas of Europe with a crew of madmen.",
      "answer": "ship of fools <MJ> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kings of this nation would take back land from the nobility in events called reductions. One rebellion in this nation was led by Sten Sture the Younger. This nation’s most infamous traitor is Archbishop Trolle, whose execution of rebels fighting for this country’s independence encouraged the Reformation here. Rene Descartes died in this country after being invited by a queen who was nicknamed “The Minerva of the North” for her interest in learning, Christina. For 10 points, name this Scandinavian nation with its capital at Stockholm.",
      "answer": "Sweden <BA> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This program named one plan \"Project 921\" because it was the first major project of 1992. This program partnered with a European counterpart for the Double Star mission. A device developed by this initiative travelled about 375 feet across the Sea of Rains before getting stuck. This program uses a family of rockets named after a 1930’s military retreat. For 10 points, identify this third national program to launch a man into orbit on the mission Shenzhou 5.",
      "answer": "Chinese space program <VP> {III}"
    },
    {
      "question": "The last house where this person’s forces killed residents was owned by Rebecca Vaughan. The only person this person confessed to killing was Margaret Whitehead, whom he killed with a fence post. He was captured by Benjamin Phipps after having marched towards Jerusalem in Southampton county following a solar eclipse. Thomas Gray wrote on the “Confessions of” [this man]. For 10 points, name this Virginian slave who led a namesake slave revolt in 1831.",
      "answer": "Nat Turner <JZ> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this empire annulled the Treaty of Surat and signed the favorable Convention of Wadgaon after the ensuing conflict. This empire's military formed gangs of bandits called pindaris. This empire's founder was a member of the Bhosle clan who once escaped Agra in a basket of sweets. Shivaji was the first peshwa of this empire, which fought three namesake wars with the British. For 10 points, name this Hindu confederacy which eclipsed the Mughal Empire.",
      "answer": "Maratha Empire <JB> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Dawes was a tanner and militia leader from this state. In this state, Federalists built a political machine called the Essex Junto, led by former Secretary of State Timothy Pickering. One disturbance in this state was sparked by the arrival of the ships, Eleanor, Dartmouth and Beaver. Harrison Gray Otis represented this state at the Hartford Convention, to which it sent the most delegates. For 10 points, name this New England state home to John Adams.",
        "answer": "Massachusetts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Massachusetts colonial judge James Otis resigned in opposition to what writs, which let British soldiers enter a residence without any notice or probable cause?",
        "answer": "writs of assistance <BA> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A leader of this city named Smaragdus built the Column of Phocas. Eutychius was the last exarch of a Byzantine client state centered on this city that fell in 751. In this city, a king who supported Leontius was stabbed to death at a banquet on the orders of the Emperor Zeno. Belisarius captured this city in 540 during the Gothic War, and Justinian and his wife were honored with a mosaic in this city’s Basilica of San Vitale. For 10 points, name this city in northern Italy that was the capital of the Ostrogoths.",
        "answer": "Ravenna"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned supporter of Leontius was what Heruli leader and first “King of Italy,” who led the Ostrogoths before being assassinated by Theodoric the Great?",
        "answer": "Flavius Odoacer <CKM> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A group of “kayaktivists” are hoping to prevent Shell Oil from using this city’s port. A project in this city, meant to replace a piece of infrastructure damaged in the 2001 Nisqually earthquake, has been stalled due to a steel pipe damaging a tunnel boring machine, Bertha. Its mayor Ed Murray signed a law increasing its minimum wage to $15 dollars an hour and has pushed for the replacement of the Alaskan Way viaduct. For 10 points, name this largest city in Washington.",
        "answer": "Seattle, Washington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What member of Socialist Alternative won election to Seattle’s City Council in 2013?",
        "answer": "Kshama Sawant <CW> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person established a statistical control unit for the XX Bomber command and instituted systems analysis with his subordinate, Charles Hitch. This Cabinet member was one of the “Whiz Kids” who revitalized the Ford Motor company. Errol Morris directed a documentary detailing eleven lessons from this person’s life. This person commissioned the Pentagon Papers to evaluate his success fighting the Vietnam War. For 10 points, name this longest serving Secretary of Defense.",
        "answer": "Robert McNamara"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which book by journalist David Halberstam negatively portrayed McNamara and other members of the Kennedy Administration cabinet?",
        "answer": "The Best and The Brightest <JZ> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This cause grew out of the earlier Language Movement and the Six-Point Movement. The atrocities committed against supporters of this cause during Operation Searchlight were discussed in a telegram sent by Archer Blood. After the success of this cause, the principles of Mujibism were implemented by the leader of the Awami League. For 10 points, name this cause which sought to turn East Pakistan into an independent country with a capital at Dhaka.",
        "answer": "Independence of Bangladesh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pakistani president during the Bangladesh War, Muhammad Yahya, held what honorific title, as did his predecessor, Muhammad Ayub?",
        "answer": "Khan <JB> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person, who lost two fingers on his left hand while serving on the “Nisshin,” was targeted in Operation Vengeance. This former Harvard student and opponent of the Tripartite Pact supposedly said that he feared that he woke a “sleeping giant” in his most famous action. This person was killed when his aircraft was shot down while inspecting troops in the Solomon islands. For 10 points, name this Japanese Admiral who planned the attack on Pearl Harbor.",
        "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Yamamoto was killed when American codebreakers in what program decoded Japanese signals to figure out where he would be?",
        "answer": "Magic <JZ> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person tabled the Clayton compromise, resulting in his stabbing by Francis Cone. This person present at the Hampton Roads Conference was the friend of Robert Toombs and backed the Compromise of 1850 in a platform named for his state. He stated that slavery was the natural condition of blacks in the “Cornerstone Speech,” and his election to the Senate in 1866 helped spur support for Reconstruction. For 10 points, name this Vice President of the Confederacy.",
        "answer": "Alexander Hamilton Stephens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Stephens represents the state of Georgia in what Washington, DC collection where historical figures are depicted?",
        "answer": "National Statuary Hall Collection <JZ> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man wrote a book which included a chapter on the ophicleide. This composer’s final symphony was written for a 200-piece wind band, and was commissioned for the tenth anniversary of the July Revolution. This creator of the Treatise on Instrumentation and Grand Funeral and Triumphal Symphony was inspired by actress Harriet Smithson to write a “March to the Scaffold.” For 10 points, name this composer of the Symphonie Fantastique.",
        "answer": "Hector Berlioz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hector Berlioz’s opera Les Troyens was modeled after what innovator of French grand opera, who dramatized the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre in Les Huguenots?",
        "answer": "Giacomo Meyerbeer <CW> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler signed the Treaty of Jam-Zapolski after Stephan Bathory invaded his country with forces that reached Pskov. This ruler legendarily had Postnik Yakovlev blinded, and created an armed group known as the streltsy. This ruler had St. Basil's Cathedral built after this ruler's forces took control of Kazan. This ruler was succeeded by Feodor I. For 10 points, name this first tsar of Russia, who accidentally killed his son and heir-apparent.",
        "answer": "Ivan the Terrible"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ivan the Terrible was one of the final rulers of what dynasty, named after a Varangian chieftain who founded Novgorod?",
        "answer": "Rurikid dynasty <JL> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this Olympics, Hans-Gunnar Liljenwall became the first Olympic athlete to be disqualified for failing a drug test. After winning six medals at this Olympics, Vera Caslaskva refused to deny having signed the Two Thousand Words. Ten days before its opening ceremonies, up to 300 students were killed in the Tlaltelolco Massacre. For 10 points, which Olympic Games were the first to be held in Latin America?",
        "answer": "1968 Summer Olympics"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the 1968 Summer Olympics, who won the gold medal in the men's high jump by performing his namesake \"flop\"?",
        "answer": "Dick Fosbury <DW> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Exceptions to this act were granted by the Webb-Pomerene Act. This act was expanded to target price discrimination by the Robinson-Patman Act, and amended with a filing requirement by the Hart-Scott-Rodino Act. Since it made strikes, picketing, and boycotts legal, this legislation could not be used against labor unions as its predecessor had been. For 10 points, name this 1914 act which amended and strengthened the 1890 Sherman Antitrust Act.",
        "answer": "Clayton Antitrust Act"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hart-Scott-Rodino Act was passed during the tenure of what president, who once claimed that \"there is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe\"?",
        "answer": "Gerald Rudolph Ford <JB> {III}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a meeting of \"Volunteers Against Bolshevism,\" Paul Collette attempted to kill this politician. This politician was the first Frenchman to be chosen as Time Magazine's Man of the Year. With Samuel Hoare, this man proposed a plan to appease Mussolini's desire to control Ethiopia. This man was arrested shortly after his December 1940 dismissal from Philippe Pétain's cabinet. For 10 points, name this Prime Minister of Vichy France.",
        "answer": "Pierre Laval"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Laval served as the Minister of Justice under what Prime Minister, who earlier attempted to outlaw war through a pact co-written with an American?",
        "answer": "Aristide Briand <KG> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE 1980 PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION",
      "prompt": "During the 1980 U.S. Presidential election...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Who defeated Jimmy Carter to become President?",
          "answer": "Ronald Wilson Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which state had the second highest number of electoral votes?",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "What current governor of California withdrew after a disastrous showing in Wisconsin?",
          "answer": "Jerry Brown"
        },
        {
          "question": "What member of a notable Democratic family failed to oust Jimmy Carter during the primaries?",
          "answer": "Ted Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "What term, combining high inflation with high unemployment, characterized the economy?",
          "answer": "stagflation"
        },
        {
          "question": "What Illinois Congressman received over six percent of the popular vote as an independent?",
          "answer": "John Bayard Anderson"
        },
        {
          "question": "What disastrous attempt to rescue hostages in Iran helped lead to Carter's defeat?",
          "answer": "Operation Eagle Claw"
        },
        {
          "question": "What former Democratic governor of Texas ran in the Republican primaries?",
          "answer": "John Bowden Connally, Jr. <DW> {II}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE ERA OF APARTHEID",
      "prompt": "During the era of apartheid, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country in which it was official policy?",
          "answer": "Republic of South Africa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military leader who became an anti-apartheid symbol during his 27-year incarceration?",
          "answer": "Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela"
        },
        {
          "question": "State President who ended the policy in 1994?",
          "answer": "F.W. de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party whose 1948 platform called for enacting the policy?",
          "answer": "National Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighborhood in which a 1976 anti-Afrikaans-education \"uprising\" took place?",
          "answer": "Soweto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for a territory in South Africa set aside for black ethnic groups during the 1950's?",
          "answer": "Bantustan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Black Consciousness Movement who died in police custody in 1977?",
          "answer": "Steve Biko"
        },
        {
          "question": "Zulu chief given the 1960 Nobel Peace Prize for his nonviolent anti-apartheid protests?",
          "answer": "Albert John Lutuli <DW> {III}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BURNT AT THE STAKE",
      "prompt": "Name the burnt at the stake...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Women accused of being what spellcasters in league with Satan?",
          "answer": "witches"
        },
        {
          "question": "What visionary commander in the Hundred Years' War, when she was only 19?",
          "answer": "Saint Joan of Arc"
        },
        {
          "question": "Thousands of Jews in which capital of Alsace?",
          "answer": "Strasbourg"
        },
        {
          "question": "What unrepentant Catholic author of Utopia?",
          "answer": "Saint Thomas More"
        },
        {
          "question": "What pre-Galileo Italian who believed in infinitely many Copernican solar systems?",
          "answer": "Giordano Bruno"
        },
        {
          "question": "What last Grand Master of the Knights Templar?",
          "answer": "Jacques du Molay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Planners of what 1683 conspiracy against England's Stuart monarch?",
          "answer": "Rye House Plot"
        },
        {
          "question": "What second-wave Lollard leader targeted by a 1414 parliament at Greyfriars?",
          "answer": "Sir John Oldcastle <MJ> {III}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A chieftain of this people wielded a bow that required fifty people to operate. Fifteen thousand members of this ethnic group, led by Barc, were baptized in 1227. Elizabeth, the wife of Stephen V, was a princess of this tribe. Led by Khan Konchak, this people scored a great victory against Prince (20 pts)",
        "Igor. This people, who formed the western branch of the Kipchak confederation, migrated westward in the thirteenth century after (10 pts)",
        "Mongol invasions threatened their homeland. For 10 points, name this nomadic Turkic people who assimilated into Hungarian society."
      ],
      "answer": "Cumans <AG> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one of this man's novels, a scholar named Barlow helps a governor's Task Force organize lesson plans about events such as Alvar Nuñez Cabeza de Vaca's murder. In 1959, this author published a novel that ends with, and coincided with, the statehood of Hawai'i. He included the indigenous trader (20 pts)",
        "Bloody Mary in a short story collection which also features an affair between Nellie Forbush and the Frenchman Emile de Becque on an (10 pts)",
        "island where American troops are stationed during World War II. For 10 points, name this American whose bulky historical fiction books include Texas and Tales of the South Pacific."
      ],
      "answer": "James Michener <MJ> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Historians sometimes call this battle the last stand of a \"Western Confederacy\" of tribes which included the Lenape leader Buckongahelas. The Legion of the United States was created in anticipation of this battle. One commander at this battle had destroyed the forces of Arthur St. Clair at the Wabash river three years prior to it. That commander, (20 pts)",
        "Blue Jacket, supported the Miami forces of (10 pts)",
        "Little Turtle here. The Treaty of Greenville solidified the territorial concessions following this battle. For 10 points, name this 1794 battle won by \"Mad\" Anthony Wayne over the natives of the Northwest Territory west of the Ohio River."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Fallen Timbers <MJ> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The theory in this book regards Ukraine and Yugoslavia as places on the edge of the \"Orthodox world.\" This book was a direct a response to, and published a year after, Francis Fukuyama's The End of History and the Last Man, which had predicted a permanent order of (20 pts)",
        "liberal democracies. This book claims that wars across a central \"fault line\" will set the (10 pts)",
        "Western and Islamic examples of the title groupings against one another. For 10 points, name this 1993 book of IR theory by Samuel Huntington, that predicted a post-Cold War world order of conflicts between large distinctive cultures."
      ],
      "answer": "The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order <MJ> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was accused after Newt Lee found notes referring to a night watchman as “night witch”. According to testimony from this man’s office boy Alonzo Mann, Jim Conley most likely committed the crime this man was accused of. William Joseph Simmons revived the KKK after leading a group that (20 pts)",
        "kidnapped this man. After receiving a life sentence, this man was taken from prison, driven to a city near Marietta, and (10 pts)",
        "hung from a tree. The Anti-Defamation League was founded in the wake of his death. For 10 points, name this factory owner accused of killing Mary Phagan, a Jewish-American lynching victim."
      ],
      "answer": "Leo Max Frank <EM> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a fire in this city, a YMCA employee named Asa Jennings saved many children as neutral British ships in its harbor played loud music to block out the screams. The Franks' Street was a center for foreign trade in this hometown of Polycarp, which was also the birthplace of the false messiah Shabbatai Zvi. As the Ottoman empire fell apart, irregular troops called (20 pts)",
        "chettes who answered to Mustafa Kemal razed this city in 1922, ending its long-lasting (10 pts)",
        "Greek community. For 10 points, name this coastal Anatolian city which was rebuilt by Turkey as Izmir."
      ],
      "answer": "Smyrna <MJ>"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Every Queen album since 1978's Jazz was recorded in this city. The album Machine Head was recorded in this city using a mobile studio owned by the Rolling Stones. \"Funky\" Claude Nobs, who helped audience members escape an incident in this city, was also a director of its famous (20 pts)",
        "jazz festival, the world’s second-largest. During an incident in this city, \"some stupid with a (10 pts)",
        "flare gun\" caused a casino to burn down during a Frank Zappa concert. For 10 points, name this city on Lake Geneva, which was immortalized as the setting of Deep Purple's \"Smoke on the Water.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Montreux, Switzerland <KG> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Captured German aircraft were offloaded into this city by the HMS Reaper as part of Operation LUSTY. Leo P. Carlin was accused of running a political machine in this city. The arrest of taxi driver John Weerd Smith and his subsequent dragging in front of the Hayes Homes project led to a (20 pts)",
        "race riot in this city during the tenure of Mayor Hugh Addonizio. Luis (10 pts)",
        "Quintana succeeded one man as mayor of this city, who received a 100 million dollar donation for this city’s schools from Mark Zuckerberg. For 10 points, name this city formerly led by Cory Booker."
      ],
      "answer": "Newark, New Jersey <EM> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader ordered an invasion that led to the Battle of Chains. This man is sometimes known by his nickname of “As-Sadiq”, or the truthful. This man fought the Ridda Wars against tribes that did not accept his authority. This man was the first to receive the title “Leader of the (20 pts)",
        "Pilgrims” when he led a party of 300 on the first Hajj conducted under Islamic Law. This man said “if you worship Allah, he is (10 pts)",
        "alive and will never die” at the end of a speech that began “if you worshipped Muhammad, he is dead.” For 10 points, name this man who Sunnis consider the first Caliph of Islam."
      ],
      "answer": "Abu Bakr <BA> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Howard Metzenbaum accused this man of never working for a living, eliciting the “Gold Star Mothers” speech from this man. This man, the chief author of the Nuclear Non- Proliferation Act, defeated Mike DeWine in one election even after being named as one of the Keating Five. In one instance, the city of Perth turned on all its (20 pts)",
        "lights as this man passed overhead, an act which was repeated during this man’s time on STS-95. His most famous accomplishment was part of the (10 pts)",
        "Friendship 7 mission. For 10 points, name this former Senator from Ohio and Mercury Seven astronaut, the first American to orbit the earth."
      ],
      "answer": "John Herschel Glenn, Jr <EM> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sumio Iijima showed a molecule comprised of only this element could appear in single- walled or multi-walled varieties. A molecule made from only this element was discovered by Kroto, Smalley and Curl at Rice University. Geim and Novoselov produced two- dimensional (20 pts)",
        "layers of atoms of this element using the \"scotch tape\" method. The first (10 pts)",
        "fullerene to be discovered was sixty atoms of this element arranged in a sphere. For 10 points, name this element that completely makes up buckyballs, graphene and their namesake \"nanotubes.\""
      ],
      "answer": "carbon <VP> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man lost an earlobe when his golden earrings were forcibly ripped out, after which he was thrown in the Mamertine Prison. This man seized control of his kingdom after murdering his half-brothers Hiempsal and Adherbal. Sallust is known for a monograph on a conflict named for this king. This man lost the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Muthul to forces under the commander Caecilius Metellus. (10 pts)",
        "Bocchus I of Mauritania betrayed this man, who was then captured and brought to Rome. For 10 points, name this king of Numidia who waged a namesake 112-105 BCE war against the Roman Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Jugurtha <CKM> {III} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 16"
    }
  ]
}